I estimate in the United States alone
there's probably 50 to 100 million
people who would benefit from
testosterone but do not take it because
it's stigmatized we can extrapolate that
to a billion people worldwide I also
think it's a lack of understanding that
hormones are front and center in human
biology and if we're dealing with all of
these lifestyle factors environmental
factors dietary factors that are
negatively affecting at home and
production it makes sense that this
field is something that people are going
to kind of need sooner or later if they
want to optimize their health longevity
and performance this has been a long
time coming we're here with Dave Lee
Dave I have been a fan for a long time I
have watched you even before I started
my clinic I've really appreciated your
content it was kind of funny same
similar to you I always hear people you
know telling me about about Dave and how
I should talk to him sometime and uh and
I had been thinking about doing it prior
to that anyway so this has been a long
time coming and uh and I think it's been
going to be great one of the first
things I I think it's prudent to
converse about especially coming from
different parts of the world so we have
we have an interesting two different
interesting perspectives the almost
Global stigmatization and demonization
of testosterone trt hormone replacement
therapy and it seems to be similar I
talk a decent amount with people from
outside of the United States and it's
it's very similar in the inadequately
addressing hormone deficiency and
hormone deficiency is pervasive and it's
just not well understood so I guess one
of the first things I would like to to
begin to to discuss is what are your
views on some of the reasons we kind of
both understand that it's not just one
thing that causes this Universal
stigmatization it's a myad of things
that kind of coales and create this big
problem if it was one thing we could
easily just fix it right like we could
uh we could just say okay here's the
problem let's re-educate and fix this
and then all of a sudden people would be
using testosterone as much as they
really should be but there tends to be a
myriad of different things that coales
and create this this massive problem
that's hard to hard to nail down hard to
pin and and hard to fix let's start
there what what do you think are some of
the innate inherent reasons for the
demonization the stigmatization yeah as
you said I think there's a lot of things
and I don't know which one you know is
the dominant thing and which one is the
supplementary thing but one thing that I
know for a fact that is part of it at
least in Australia is that because
testosterone is classified as a
performance enhancing drug technically
in terms of how they classified at least
same with DHEA which is why DHEA is
prescription only in Australia as well
um it's scheduled alongside the other
anabolic steroids not alongside the
other sex hormones so I think that the
way that it's scheduled in terms of it's
deemed a drug of abuse it's more
difficult to have prescribed a lot of
doctors are afraid of it being
prescribed because they think that
they're going to lose their medical
license if they give a private
prescription for testosterone because
it's not going going through an
endocrinologist and I think that's part
of it in terms of going a little bit
down the conspiracy Rabbit Hole straight
off the bat I dropped out of neuros
Psychiatry uh when I was at University
because I was going into the course
thinking I was going to learn how to
heal the brain and learn why so many
people were experiencing these kind of
lowgrade mental health disorders you
know across the board I quickly leared
that that's not what you learn in that
degree you just learn how to drug people
but I also think that a important
component of this and I think it's a
significant one is that the
pharmaceutical industry is very heavily
involved in how medications are
prescribed I mean when you do a medical
degree a lot of it is learning to
prescribe medicine which in the western
Paradigm is Pharmaceuticals and because
testosterone has been off patent for so
long and I mean you can put a new Ester
on it and you know give it a Fresh coat
of paint but it's very difficult to make
money on bioidentical hormone
replacement therapy and I think that
trickles into a lot of things in terms
terms of the doctors a lot of the time
will push female birth control instead
of bioidentical progesterone for a
progesterone deficiency so it it
trickles into women as well but you can
go as far back as looking at the early
uh prescribing guidelines for pregnant
alone before cortico steroids were
developed and then corticosteroids very
quickly replaced pregnanolone in the
prescribing guidelines because lo and
behold in a clinical trial they were
more efficacious for what they were
treating but they also had a myriad more
side effects but you that's not the
problem so I think patenting medications
is a factor and I think that the
pharmaceutical industry's influence in
the way that the medical Paradigm is
structured and operated and continues to
evolve kind of shoots bioidentical
hormone replacement therapy in the foot
because a less profitable medical
intervention is always by default going
to be alternative under that model so I
think those are two big factors the
performance-enhancing side as well as
the pharmaceutical industry but I also
think there's just a lot of
misunderstanding around the body being a
series of interconnected systems which
is something I've been speaking about
for a long time and the reason that I
got into hormones I mean I wasn't into
like a health and fitness and sports
background I was coming from a mental
health background and I gravitated
towards testosterone because I was like
well hormones are the kind of marionette
puppet Masters that of run the show for
for everything so
if the body is sick I mean I Had a Brain
Injury that no one could diagnose and no
one could tell me how to heal and my
idea was well if I can set the body up
to heal itself and then put the right
nutrients and the right stimulus in then
maybe I can recover and I very quickly
worked out that you had to have an
optimal hormone environment to do that
so I also think it's a lack of
understanding that hormones are front
and center in human biology and if we're
dealing with all of these lifestyle
factors environmental factors dietary
factors that are negatively affecting
our home and production it makes sense
that this field is something that people
are going to kind of need sooner or
later if they want to optimize their
health longevity and performance yeah
that was very wellstead very articulate
and pretty much spot on what I see like
so you know getting to the root of what
you're saying and and everything you
said is absolutely concur with that the
fundamental foundational problem with
educating providers about hormones right
and you're right so when you look at
when we at the United States and and it
probably works similarly to this and
around medical schools the
pharmaceutical companies do fund medical
schools they have a say in the
curriculum and they're going to teach
towards the medications that make them
the money right and and as you indicated
testosterone the patents up it's been
around for 80 years it doesn't generate
a lot of Revenue um because it can be
compounded it's you know kind of easily
made also continuing medical education
for providers the pharmaceutical
companies run continuing medical
education and again they're going to
teach around the medications that are
going to make them the most money I mean
this is just kind of factual right but
like when we if we want to start talking
about yeah some of the conspiracy like
is there intentional suppression of
testosterone because it there is more
money made um treating The Fallout from
low testosterone than there is actually
treating the root of the problem and
getting people's testosterone I don't
have any direct evidence I've looked I
don't have any direct evidence of
intentional supression a lot of people a
lot of conspiracy theorists would say
yeah of course of course they're doing
that and so another reason and and
you're right A lot of it has to do with
sports as as ridiculous as as it is the
idea that in in the United States it was
Biden specifically said well I don't
know what's going to happen with
baseball games are people going to show
up so it was kind of like it like a lot
of oh and then Ben Johnson in the
Olympics you know tested positive for
for win straw so it had a lot to do with
um with sports they wanted to maintain
this Integrity in sports so therefore
we're going to suppress this massively
beneficial uh treatment protocol just
because we you know we want people to
show up to baseball games right so in
this period though when when the
stigmatization was starting we have like
worldwide organizations like wada that
are making sure that there's Integrity
in sports but also demonizing them at
the same time and there seem to be some
really poorly really poorly run studies
a series of them starting from the
beginning of the stigmatization which I
would say is the late 80s early 90s um
United States testosterone became a
controlled substance in the 199 steroid
control act so around that time there
was a lot of studies that came out that
showed all the massive benefits of
testosterone and other derivatives of
testosterone and then from the late 80s
to about 2016 is is when I see like the
last really poorly really biased study
and there was a lot of studies that came
out that were just incredibly biased and
that found some of the classic side
effects that we now know are not not
accurate that are not correct studies
that showed testosterone cause cardiac
issues right we now know that's not true
at the time that there was about four
four studies showing that testosterone
may cause cardiac issues there was over
a hundred studies that showed not only
did it not cause cardiac issues but a
lot of the studies found that it was
actually cardioprotective which we now
know right and that book is closed on
that like we have we have closed that
chapter testosterone does not cause
cardiac issues however why did the FDA
in our country decide to promulgate the
four studies and put a blackbox warning
on testosterone kind of due to these
four studies and instead of listening to
the other hundred that that showed
something different and those studies
were poorly run and now are widely
discredited and the original authors
have done retractions so one of the
cardiac studies was as simple as they
had a math error now as a scientist how
do you publish a study with a math error
and and why would it be so why would
these studies be so incredibly biased
like it almost seems like for a
professional scientist to publish
something so quickly as to have a math
error in it when you we redid math by
the way we found that it showed the
opposite that testosterone actually was
cardioprotective and not caused adverse
cardio events but why would these
incredibly bias studies come out all in
the same era right when testosterone was
being so demonized like it almost seems
like there was incentivization to write
these studies in a biased manner that
that showed this like we don't have any
proof but um it's hard not to believe so
also testosterone causes prostate cancer
we now know that's not true testosterone
increases the risk of blood clot
clotting disorders and we now know that
that's not true in fact I found a study
that shows that testosterone actually
reduces procoagulation and reduces
throbin produces anti- throbbin and
actually fibron fibrinolysis which
reduces existing clouds you know I think
a lot of these studies had a lot to do
with it too you can still see it like
whenever a the media was a big problem
too they when these studies when the
blackbox warning was put on testosterone
the media would just get a hold of these
and promate all of this stigmatized
information that we now know to be
exactly the opposite so the the media
had a problem too and you can still see
it we just watched a video where where
they asked about the the huge increase
in use of testosterone and of course you
have a cardiologist on there who he's
older and he's going by the Antiquated
Notions and Dogma from decades ago and
he's saying oh yeah testosterone causes
all these problems and it's just not
true so part of the problem is the media
asking the wrong people like you're
asking a cardiologist one thing we know
about if you go to medical school you do
not learn about these hormones so you're
asking the wrong people people who don't
actually learn about these things and
they learn the little information they
do learn is the Antiquated Notions and
Dogma from decades ago the wrong
information all of this kind of comes
combines and and creates this massive
stigma massive demonization and
inadequately addressing hormone
deficiency yeah absolutely and the
couple of things I'll add on that
which one one thing is has been very
interesting for me living over here in
Lithuania and for those who don't know
where Lithuania is it's a very normal
reaction to have I didn't know where it
was either uh it's technically northern
Europe a lot of people think of it as
Eastern Europe but it's the one of the
three Baltic States north of Poland so
up until uh 91 Lithuania was part of the
Soviet Union and as a result of that we
have this kind of interesting
amalgamation of Western medicine and
Soviet medicine and I find Soviet
medicine very interesting because
because Soviet medicine is actually
built a lot around peptides I mean
they're the ones who came out with the
bior regulated peptides people often
hear about things like cmax seank
cerebral lion they're stocked at the
local pharmacy in my town so these
compounds are actually part of our
medical system and the interesting thing
with the medical system over here and
you know all medical systems are flawed
but the thing that I found over here is
that they're very focused on root cause
and they're very focused on recovery so
recently I've been dealing with a
sciatica issue and I've been researching
you know alphal lolic acid infusions
because they've been shown to be
beneficial for nerve regeneration for
diabetic uh neuropathy uh and those
studies were actually done over here in
Eastern Europe and lo and behold you go
down to a local general practitioner and
they go yep we'll give you 10 infusions
of ala come in every three days and
we'll do 10 infusions and it's covered
by your insurance nothing to pay and
this was very interesting for me because
when you'd speak to the the doctor the
sessions would be a lot longer they'd
come out with a big plan for you
everything would be subsidized that you
actually needed but you know I was sent
off with like high do B1 I was sent off
with a bunch of nutrient therapies as
well and they still have the Western
Pharmaceuticals as part of their you
know their toolbox but they seem to be
very much orientated around fixing
people to help you get healthy and
strong so that you don't burden the
healthare system whereas without going
too far down the conspiracy Rabbit Hole
I do kind of one to two things I do
wonder if the Western Medical model is
based on this idea of keeping people
sick enough just to pay their taxes but
not healthy enough that they'll push
back against the system and I also
wonder with all the technology we have
in 2025 would we still be able to be
governed if every man was walking around
with high testosterone like I I really
kind of ask and go like I I think that
that would lead to a problem and I think
that there has to be some kind of
awareness of that I mean one thing
that's very interesting when you do uh
neuros Psychiatry is you learn about
this thing called operant conditioning
which is basically like training to
follow rules and they find that
everything from ssris to antis
psychotics to even you know
dexamphetamine or amphetamine
derivatives methylphenidate ryin all
increase operant conditioning whereas
one of the only molecules that reduces
operant conditioning is testosterone
which makes sense to me yeah
soina when you look at something like
that and you go man if I was running the
world I probably wouldn't want any
everyone on this this could be a bit of
a problem but it's uh it's it's
definitely interesting when you when you
look into it because I remember when I
was first looking at all of the kind of
brain mechanisms of action of
testosterone and kind of comparing it to
the mechanism of action of you know
things like off Lael anti-depressants
like over in the US things like uh
wellin ropien is quite common in
Australia we only use it for seasoning
smoking but I was kind of comparing it
to all these different uh psychoactive
compounds but particularly compounds
that worked on dopamine and when I was
looking at how testosterone worked how
thyroid worked how DHEA balone worked I
was going hang on this is the kind of
perfect mechanism of action if it came
to being like what would be the dream
designer psychiatric medication that we
could create for people I was like it
would it would be if all of these
hormones were optimal in the brain and
then the brain would just function the
way that it should and it's
to to me it's it's very interesting that
the the model that we seem to be
defaulted to in the west is creating
patients for life and I know that
testosterone replacement therapy is also
an ongoing treatment so there's there's
a bit of irony to that but I always
found it very interesting in when you
are studying Psychiatry that there's
this very strong preference towards the
new medications that are under patent
because you know for people who don't
know who are listening when a
pharmaceutical company develops a new
drug you get an 8-year period that you
basically have the patent for it so
other companies can't make a a generic
for it which is why up until you know
the recent years you know talil Calis
was like insanely expensive and then it
got very cheap and available the patent
expired and this is you know the idea of
this is that it's to recoup your
research and development costs AKA make
an absolute killing and you know
pharmaceutical Industries are are
profitable businesses and you know their
private businesses run to make a profit
so that makes sense but I found it very
interesting that in Psychiatry the
newest drug that was under patent also
just happened to be the best drug that
we had and I'd be sitting there going
well hang on this medication sounds
quite novel but because it's new we
don't have any long-term studies on it
so why are we preferring these novel
medications that are under patent over
these older medications that are tried
and true that work well they're cheap
and available in generic and they
basically go sh maybe you should drop
out of this degree stop asking questions
um so it's um look it's interesting and
and the problem that you're alluding to
which is really important than you know
people in America think it's bad I mean
over here in Eastern Europe I mean the
the stigma is a hundred times worse but
it's um the problem is that people are
either stigmatized in terms of they feel
like they're cheating or they'll be
judged or there's something wrong with
them if they need corate replacement
therapy but then also if they get over
that barrier
they're then scared that if they
take the actual optimal amount of
testosterone which is one thing that I
know that we agree on because I've seen
your take on it which is very important
which that a lot of the time people are
going oh yeah I need trt but I don't
want to take too much because I don't
have a heart attack at prostate cancer
and die which you know that's that's
going to happen from hypogonadism not
having you know optimal antigen levels
but people are either afraid of going on
it out of principle or they're afraid of
what it's going to do to them if they
actually correct their hormone
deficiency and I think that fear and
anxiety and stigma is leading I would
hate to think the number you know
thousands tens of thousands hundreds of
thousands I don't even know but so many
men who need this treatment who aren't
seeking it Jud to being misinformed yeah
I couldn't agree with you more and I I
think the number is is significantly
north of that so you and I both can we
can walk around in public and we can
point out hormone deficiency like I can
see it just by the way people form just
by the way they're they're walking or or
act you know so like I estimate in the
United States alone there's probably 50
to 100 million people who would benefit
from hormon from testosterone but do not
take it because it's stigmatized we can
extrapolate that to a billion people
worldwide
[Music]